<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Julie Pagano</title>
  <subtitle>Julie's little corner of the internet.</subtitle>
  <id>http://juliepagano.com/blog/</id>
  <link href="http://juliepagano.com/blog/"/>
  <link href="http://juliepagano.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-03-10T05:39:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Julie Pagano</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Ally Smells: Boundaries</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2014/03/10/ally-smells-boundaries/"/>
    <id>/blog/2014/03/10/ally-smells-boundaries/</id>
    <published>2014-03-10T05:39:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-03-10T05:39:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Pagano</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post frankly discusses issues related to boundary violations. It may be difficult to read. I recommend reviewing the content warnings below before deciding to proceed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Content warnings: boundary violations, predatory behavior, ableism, *ist language, sexual assault, and possibly others&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently covered a bunch of &lt;a href="/blog/2014/02/26/bad-ally-quiz/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;bad ally&amp;rdquo; behaviors&lt;/a&gt;. Some of the items on that list are downright awful, and some of them are more akin to the ally equivalent of a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_smell"&gt;&amp;ldquo;code smell&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. They&amp;rsquo;re not that awful in isolation, but they are often a sign of deeper problems. The more they occur, the worse those problems probably are. I am working on exploring some of these &lt;a href="/blog/tags/ally-smells/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;ally smells&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I am digging into a pretty sensitive topic: boundaries. This can range from a tiny mistake to an ally smell all the way up to a horrifying predatory situation. In this post, I am going to focus on boundary violations from people who want to be or claim to be allies. Additional discussions of boundary issues are important, but that&amp;rsquo;s another post for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you push or disrespect their boundaries (e.g. continuing a conversation when asked to stop, touching someone without permission)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the content of this post may make you upset or angry. I strongly recommend giving yourself some time to sit and think on it. If you want to be a good ally, learning to respect boundaries is critical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="boundaries"&gt;Boundaries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_boundaries"&gt;Personal boundaries&lt;/a&gt; are guidelines, rules or limits that a person creates to identify for themselves what are reasonable, safe and permissible ways for other people to behave around them and how they will respond when someone steps outside those limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boundaries can be small or huge. Seemingly inconsequential or horrifyingly important. They all matter to the people who set them. They all should be respected, when possible**.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not matter if a boundary makes sense to you. It does not matter if it seems inconsequential to you. Boundaries are the prerogative of the person who sets them. You do not know that person&amp;rsquo;s story, and they are not obligated to justify their boundaries to you. That touch that seems insignificant to you may be uncomfortably intimate for someone else. That interaction that is fine with others may trigger someone&amp;rsquo;s PTSD. You do not know more about someone than they know about themselves. Trust that they know what they are doing when they set a boundary with you, even if you do not understand why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When someone sets a boundary with you they are saying &amp;ldquo;no.&amp;rdquo; No means no. Do not push people on their boundaries or ask for explanations that are not readily given. Doing these things indicates that you do not respect their boundaries. For many people, saying &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; once, setting a boundary, is difficult enough. Do not put them in a position where they must repeatedly do so. No means no the first time. Pushing them on it suggests a hope that you can wear them down, which is problematic at best and predatory at worst. &lt;strong&gt;No means no.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** &lt;em&gt;I say &amp;ldquo;when possible&amp;rdquo; here because there will be situations where you cannot avoid violating a boundary (e.g. you trip and accidentally touch someone without permission). However this should be the exception, not the rule. Do not use this language to try to &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rules_lawyer"&gt;rules lawyer&lt;/a&gt; your way around respecting boundaries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are some examples of boundaries. All of the items below have happened to myself or people I know (often repeatedly) from people who claimed to be or wanted to be allies. They are not theoreticals. This is not an exhaustive list and should not be treated as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples:-physical"&gt;Examples: Physical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hugging someone without permission (many people give close friends implicit permission).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touching someone in potentially intimate locations (e.g. small of the back, leg, neck) without permission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touching someone intimately without permission (many people give their partners implicit permission).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touching someone in a way they have explicitly asked you not to, even if that form of touch is normal for others (e.g. handshakes, hugs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touching someone in a way that causes them to be visibly or audibly uncomfortable, even if they do not explicitly ask you to stop. (Note: subtle cues may be difficult for some non-neurotypical people to pick up on.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing to touch someone when they have asked you to stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invading someone&amp;rsquo;s personal space. A common case is standing very close to someone (appropriate distance may vary by situation and cultural background).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to make someone feel bad for setting a physical boundary with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples:-language-(verbal-or-in-text-format)"&gt;Examples: Language (verbal or in text format)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saying sexually suggestive things to or about someone unless you have a relationship where that is considered appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking to someone in a way they have explicitly asked you not to, even if that type of speech is normal for others (e.g. rape jokes, sexist/racist/ableist/*ist language).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking to someone in a way that causes them to be visibly or audibly uncomfortable, even if they do not explicitly ask you to stop. (Note: subtle cues may be difficult for some non-neurotypical people to pick up on.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing to engage with someone on a specific topic when they have asked you to stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing to engage with someone when they have asked you to cease contact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asking someone you do not know very well about sensitive or private information (e.g. genitalia, sexual assault). This includes digging for details when they provide some high level information on a sensitive topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using slurs directed at a group that person is a member of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being verbally abusive and/or threating to someone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bringing up private information about someone, such as where they live. This can easily be perceived as a threat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disclosing private information about someone without their permission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to make someone feel bad for setting a language boundary with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples:-third-parties"&gt;Examples: Third Parties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sending a third party to speak to someone after they have asked you to stop speaking with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contacting someone&amp;rsquo;s friends and acquaintances to try to get them to speak with you when they have asked you to cease direct contact with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encouraging third parties to push boundaries someone has set with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encouraging third parties to discourage someone from setting boundaries with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encouraging third parties to discourage someone from calling out boundaries you have violated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempting to discredit someone to others for setting boundaries with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to get third parties to make someone feel bad for setting a boundary with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples:-potentially-subtle-boundaries"&gt;Examples: Potentially Subtle Boundaries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interrupting a semi-private conversation between people you do not know well, particularly when they are discussing a sensitive topic. This works in person and online. Yes, they are in a public space, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you are invited if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a context with the people involved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regularly contacting someone who never engages with you. This is common on places like social networks and email. If you contact someone with great regularity and they never (or almost never) respond to you, there is a good chance you are pushing a boundary, and they are trying to ignore you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixating on someone who you do not have a close relationship with (e.g. writing blog posts about them without asking first, regularly mentioning them on social media).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asking someone if they&amp;rsquo;re talking about you when they say something vague. Most of the time, if someone wanted to call you out specifically, they would have done so. Vagueness is usually intentional and pushing someone to be explicit is often pushing a boundary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complaining about spaces you are not allowed at or attempting to enter those spaces anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="power-dynamics"&gt;Power Dynamics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power dynamics are a huge part of pushing boundaries. Boundaries are often different when power imbalances are involved. When you have a position of power over someone, it is more difficult for them to set clear boundaries with you or reassert those boundaries when they are crossed for fear of repercussions. If you care about respecting the boundaries of others, it is critical for you to pay attention to and be aware of power dynamics. This is especially critical for you to be sensitive to when you are more likely to be in a position of power. As an ally, there is very likely to be a power differential because you are in a privileged position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are some examples of power dynamics. Some power dynamics are obvious and explicit. Others are less clear. They all are important and matter. Predators often prey on more subtle power dynamics because they are easier to get away with. Take the steps to draw a clear distinction between yourself and them by paying closer attention to these dynamics. This is not an exhaustive list and should not be treated as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: many of the examples below mention the potential for harm. The power dynamic exists because you could do those things, even if you think it is clear that you would not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples:-work-&amp;amp;-school"&gt;Examples: Work &amp;amp; School&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you have an explicit position of power over them codified in your work/school relationship?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are their boss, their boss&amp;rsquo;s boss, or even higher up the chain of command at their job. You directly have the power to punish or fire them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a professor, teacher, or other educator and they are a student. You directly have the power to negatively impact their academic/educational achievement and performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you have a position of power over them related to your work/school relationship?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are their team lead, supervisor, mentor, or something similar at their job. You are not their boss, but you have the ability to negatively impact their work environment. You may be close with their boss (or higher ups) and be able to indirectly impact their chances of being punished or fired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a teaching assistant, mentor, or something similar in an academic/educational environment. You cannot directly impact their achievement and performance, but you can negatively impact the environment for them. You may be close with their professor, teacher, or others with more direct power over the student and be able to indirectly impact their academic/educational achievement and performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you have an implicit position of power over them related to your work/school relationship?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a colleague, peer, or something similar at their job. Your power over them may come from things like seniority at the workplace, more years of experience, or a social relationship with others in a position of power. You have the ability to indirectly impact their work environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are another student or colleague in an academic/educational environment. Your power over them may come from things like higher achievement, seniority in school, or a social relationship with others in a position of power. You have the ability to indirectly impact their academic/educational environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples:-community"&gt;Examples: Community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you have an explicit position of power?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a known organizer of a conference, user group, open source project, or other community group. You have the ability to make someone unwelcome at these groups or even explicitly ban them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you have an implicit position of power?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a speaker at a conference, user group, or other event. You have the ability to use your platform and celebrity to make events uncomfortable or unwelcoming for someone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are a well known member of a community through work, speaking, open source contributions, or other means. You have the ability to use your celebrity to discredit others or make them uncomfortable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="examples:-characteristics"&gt;Examples: Characteristics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you have any characteristics that may give you a position of power?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you much larger and stronger than the other person?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you a member of a privileged group that has historically oppressed a group the other person is a member of?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you a member of a group that is in the majority in your work or academic environment while the other person is a member of group that is in the minority?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you a member of a group that is statistically likely to harm the other person?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="why-is-it-important?"&gt;Why Is It Important?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be asking yourself why are boundaries so critical? Why am I making such a big deal about this? In the opening of this post, I mentioned that boundary violations can range from a tiny mistake to an ally smell all the way up to a horrifying predatory situation. Boundary violations are a big deal, even when they are small, because they are often a sign of things to come. A symptom of something more sinister than an accident. A red flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I saying that everyone who violates a boundary is a dangerous predator? No, I am not. Definitely not. Plenty of good people I know and trust have made mistakes with boundaries. I have made mistakes with boundaries. Not all people who violate boundaries are predators, but all predators violate boundaries. It is often impossible for the person on the receiving end of the violation to tell the difference and guessing wrong can have dire consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predators often start with small boundary violations that might seem inconsequential in isolation. Seeing what they can get away with. Slowly escalating. Others have referred to this as &lt;a href="http://yesmeansyesblog.wordpress.com/2010/09/14/the-boiling-frog-principle-of-boundary-violation/"&gt;The Boiling Frog Principle Of Boundary Violation&lt;/a&gt;. This is why even small mistakes can be seen as a red flag, particularly if they happen repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a popular post titled &lt;a href="http://kateharding.net/2009/10/08/guest-blogger-starling-schrodinger%E2%80%99s-rapist-or-a-guy%E2%80%99s-guide-to-approaching-strange-women-without-being-maced/"&gt;Schrödinger’s Rapist&lt;/a&gt; that explores some of these interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you approach me in public, you are Schrödinger’s Rapist. You may or may not be a man who would commit rape. I won’t know for sure unless you start sexually assaulting me. I can’t see inside your head, and I don’t know your intentions. If you expect me to trust you—to accept you at face value as a nice sort of guy—you are not only failing to respect my reasonable caution, you are being cavalier about my personal safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boundary violations are exhausting, especially for people at an increased risk of being targeted by predators. Dealing with these issues regularly means having to be on guard and evaluate safety most of the time. A constant white noise of evaluating risk and hoping your assessment is correct. Mental energy that could be spent elsewhere if boundaries were not regularly being violated. Allies can take on some of that load by being mindful and avoiding boundary violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boundary violations can reduce comfort and access to certain resources and spaces for people. For example, someone may no longer feel comfortable attending events with someone who has violated their boundaries because they are concerned it will continue or escalate. Someone may lose a mentor who can help them professionally because they push boundaries, and it makes them uncomfortable. There can be very real personal and professional consequences of boundary violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="steps-to-improve"&gt;Steps to Improve&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how I said at the beginning that this post may upset you? Your first step here is to sit with this. Give yourself some time to think on it. Maybe read it a few times. Push past the potential upset you have about this information. If you want to be a good ally, you need to work on respecting boundaries. It is ongoing work that is not necessarily easy, but is very important. This is something I try to work on regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, recognize that you are going to fuck up. We all do. Take responsibility for your mistakes. See my post &lt;a href="/blog/2014/01/06/on-making-mistakes/"&gt;about making mistakes&lt;/a&gt; for suggestions on how to respond when called out on pushing or violating boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be thoughtful. Be empathetic. If a little part of your brain says &amp;ldquo;this might be inappropriate&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;this might make someone uncomfortable,&amp;rdquo; err on the side of not doing that thing. Erring on the side of asking explicit permission is usually going to be better than erring on the side of violating someone&amp;rsquo;s boundaries. It can be awkward to ask if you&amp;rsquo;re not used to it, but practice makes perfect and people will appreciate the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be ok with hearing a &amp;ldquo;no.&amp;rdquo; Make it easy for people to tell you &amp;ldquo;no.&amp;rdquo; When you are told &amp;ldquo;no,&amp;rdquo; respect it. If possible, learn to pay attention to more subtle boundary setting from people who may have difficulty explicitly saying a clear &amp;ldquo;no.&amp;rdquo; If not possible to pick up on these cues, be clear with people that you need more explicit feedback. If someone&amp;rsquo;s boundaries are in conflict with your own boundaries, state your boundaries and, if possible, work with them to find a compromise that is amenable to both of you. If it&amp;rsquo;s not possible for you to respect someone&amp;rsquo;s stated boundaries, avoid them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, if you have a problem with violating boundaries, decrease your access to situations where you are likely to violate them. It is &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; responsibility to decrease the problem, not of those on the receiving end to try to avoid it. If you find yourself regularly violating boundaries, get help. Consider getting help from a friend with a better understanding of boundaries. If you think it is a serious problem related to mental health concerns (e.g. addiction, social anxiety, being non-neurotypical), consider getting help from a mental health professional. They are trained to assist with these sorts of things and help you work on it. Asking for help is not a sign of weakness or failure. It is committing yourself to improvement, so you do not harm others.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ally Smells: Appropriation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2014/02/28/ally-smells-appropriation/"/>
    <id>/blog/2014/02/28/ally-smells-appropriation/</id>
    <published>2014-02-28T06:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-02-28T06:30:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Pagano</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently covered a bunch of &lt;a href="/blog/2014/02/26/bad-ally-quiz/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;bad ally&amp;rdquo; behaviors&lt;/a&gt;. Some of the items on that list are downright awful, and some of them are more akin to the ally equivalent of a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_smell"&gt;&amp;ldquo;code smell&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. They&amp;rsquo;re not that awful in isolation, but they are often a sign of deeper problems. The more they occur, the worse those problems probably are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to explore some of these &amp;ldquo;ally smells&amp;rdquo; a bit more. Let&amp;rsquo;s start by talking about appropriation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-is-appropriation?"&gt;What is appropriation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start at the beginning. We need a shared working definition of &amp;ldquo;appropriation&amp;rdquo; to continue this discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ap·pro·pri·ate&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;verb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt; take (something) for one&amp;rsquo;s own use, typically without the owner&amp;rsquo;s permission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a dictionary definition of appropriate that is relevant to this discussion. The &amp;ldquo;somethings&amp;rdquo; in this conversation are the lived experiences and struggles of members of oppressed groups. The people doing the &amp;ldquo;taking&amp;rdquo; are privileged allies that are not members of those oppressed groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue of ownership gets a bit tricky here. Can one person give you permission to use the struggles of the group? What about a dozen? Or a hundred? Do you have to ask every individual member of that group for permission? Individuals can choose to give you permission to use their specific personal experiences. However, no one person or even a collection of people can give you the rights to the lived experiences and struggles of the group as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="appropriation-of-platform"&gt;Appropriation of platform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you frequently speak/write/present about the oppressed group without first suggesting that a program/publication/event/etc. speak to members of that group instead?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Privileged people who are known for being allied to an oppressed group will often be offered a platform to speak about the group&amp;rsquo;s experiences and issues that impact them. Platforms like an interview on a tv show or podcast. Platforms like writing for a blog or publication. Platforms like presenting at conferences or other events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are allies being offered a platform to speak about these issues instead of people who are actually members of the group being discussed? People who know the issues more intimately because they have lived them. People who care about them more passionately because it directly impacts them. People who cannot put it aside when it gets too hard because it is their life, and they must experience it daily whether they want to or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, why are allies accepting these offers? If you are a good ally, surely you know at least a handful of talented members of the group being discussed that would love to have access to a platform to share their insights. These are &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; lives, not yours, and they should get priority in speaking about them. If you insist on appropriating their experiences, you should at least demand that they be given a platform too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good allies focus on listening and support. Regularly speaking on behalf of those you are allied with is doing neither. Pushing for them to be given a platform supports them and provides you with yet another avenue to listen and learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most things, these are not absolutes, and there are exceptions. Spaces focused on allies helping each other learn is a reasonable place to take a platform. It can also be useful for an ally to speak up in cases where it is unsafe for members of the group to do so. Err on the side of promoting those you are allied with over promoting yourself on these topics. If you do promote yourself, do so in moderation. Making a career out of speaking on behalf of the group you are allied with is problematic because it eschews such moderation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="appropriation-of-work"&gt;Appropriation of work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you take credit for the work of members of the group you are allied with? Without also giving them credit? While claiming they did not do the work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some privileged people not only appropriate the experiences of those they are allied with, but also their work. There are a lot of different variations on this, so I am going to focus on the ones I see most frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, again with the definitions. What do I mean by &amp;ldquo;work&amp;rdquo; here? I am talking about physical or mental effort done in order to achieve something specific for or related to the oppressed group. This work includes creating safer spaces, empowering members of the group, improving representation of the group in specific areas, educating people about issues relevant to the group, and much, much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One form of appropriating work is using the work of people you are allied with and taking all or most of the credit for it. This makes me think of the trope where a woman presents an idea in a meeting, is ignored, and then a man presents it as his own and is praised for his great idea. I hope I do not have to explain why this is a problem. A great way to turn this behavior on its head is to provide full credit to the original creators and call out the people who only listened when you presented it as your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common situation is when an ally attempts to take over work that members of the group are focusing on. They insist they know best about how to address the systemic inequalities that impact oppressed people. They are frequently wrong and respond poorly when told this. They might create their own modified version of the work that ignores feedback about why their approach is problematic. They might reuse the work and not credit the original creators. Or worst of all, they might claim the original creators did no work at all. This is harmful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of oppressed groups often have to work twice as hard to receive half the credit and traction that privileged people do. When privileged allies use their position to dismiss that work or try to take credit for it as their own, they are making the situation worse. A good ally should use their position to support and promote the work of those they are allied with while ensuring that those who did the work receive credit for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some forms of work have existed long enough that one could argue they have entered the public domain and no longer &lt;em&gt;belong&lt;/em&gt; to the people who did the groundwork. I still urge you to be careful about appropriating that work, particularly without a great deal of self-education and understanding of the context it was created in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="what-now?"&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been writing a lot lately about allies for two main reasons: to improve the quality of allies I interact with as a woman and to work on improving myself as an ally to groups where I have the position of privilege. We all fuck up, and that is ok as long as we &lt;a href="/blog/2014/01/06/on-making-mistakes/"&gt;respond well to being called on those mistakes&lt;/a&gt; and work on improving. I&amp;rsquo;ve definitely made the mistakes of appropriating the platforms and work of others. I am trying to be better about this because it is important. I hope you will do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bad Ally Quiz</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2014/02/26/bad-ally-quiz/"/>
    <id>/blog/2014/02/26/bad-ally-quiz/</id>
    <published>2014-02-27T04:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-02-27T04:30:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Pagano</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The topic of bad &amp;ldquo;allies&amp;rdquo; has come up a lot lately. Some people want to know how to identify bad allies.
Others want to know if they are being bad allies. Below is a list of common issues in the ever popular
internet quiz style to help you determine if yourself or someone else might be a bad ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not about any one specific person. It is a collection of issues myself and others
have seen repeatedly from people claiming to be allies. If you take this personally or think
it&amp;rsquo;s about you, you might just be a bad ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So come one, come all, and take the bad ally quiz! The points are mostly made up, but they sure do matter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="quiz"&gt;Quiz&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give yourself points for each item that applies, even if it only applies sometimes. Items without a specified value are worth 1 point. For points assigned &amp;ldquo;per incident,&amp;rdquo; count all incidents from the last year. Be honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="words"&gt;Words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you spend a lot of time telling people what a &amp;ldquo;good ally&amp;rdquo; you are?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you claim that you never make mistakes or act in an oppressive way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you complain about spaces that only allow members of an oppressed group because you cannot be involved?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you use patronizing language (e.g. referring to an adult as a child) when speaking with or about people in the group you are allied to? &lt;em&gt;(20 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you use slurs when speaking with or about people in the group you are allied to? &lt;em&gt;(1000 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="interactions-with-the-people-you-are-allied-with"&gt;Interactions with the people you are allied with&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you demand that people educate you (instead of seeking to educate yourself)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you demand they give you time or attention (e.g. expecting advice on demand, requesting they give you personalized reviews of articles)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you tell them to fix a specific issue because they are part of a group (e.g. demanding they speak at a conference, insisting they write a post on a specific topic)? &lt;em&gt;(10 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you tell them how to speak or behave?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you &lt;a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Tone_argument"&gt;tone police&lt;/a&gt; (e.g. telling them to be nicer, &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;ll catch more flies with honey&amp;rdquo;)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you &lt;a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Concern_troll"&gt;concern troll&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you accuse people of overreacting, being too sensitive, or blowing things out of proportion?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you only ally yourself with members of the group who fit your idea of a &amp;ldquo;model minority&amp;rdquo; (look, act, and/or behave a certain way) or who agree with you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you treat the group like a monolith (i.e. assume they all think and act the same way and want the same things)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you dismiss their personal experiences?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you tell them what tactics to use when fighting oppression?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you use other members of the group to validate your behavior (e.g. I have a black friend, I&amp;rsquo;m married to a woman)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you demand praise or acknowledgment of your allyship or specific acts as an ally?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you tend to dominate conversations instead of letting others speak?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you play &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="http://www.shakesville.com/2013/10/liss-says-stuff-3-devils-advocate.html"&gt;devil&amp;rsquo;s advocate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; when discussing issues important to them?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you ask people about sensitive issues (e.g. assault, genitalia, sexuality)? &lt;em&gt;(10 points)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you push or disrespect their boundaries (e.g. continuing a conversation when asked to stop, touching someone without permission)? &lt;em&gt;(30 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have members of the group you are allied with called you a bad ally or said you were not an ally at all? &lt;em&gt;(100 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="making-mistakes"&gt;Making mistakes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you mentioned your status as an ally when called out on mistakes or bad behavior? &lt;em&gt;(5 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you try to play off mistakes as a joke? &lt;em&gt;(10 points)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you act defensively when called out on mistakes or bad behavior? &lt;em&gt;(5 points)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you get angry and lash out when called out on mistakes or bad behavior? &lt;em&gt;(20 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you make the same mistakes over and over again? &lt;em&gt;(10 points)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you fail to evaluate and understand your privilege?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you laugh at jokes at the expense of the group you are allied with?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you make jokes at the expense of the group you are allied with? &lt;em&gt;(10 points)&lt;/em&gt; Frequently? &lt;em&gt;(100 points)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you sit quietly by when others say or do things that harm the group you are allied with?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you only a fair weather ally (i.e. you only help when things are easy or benefit you)? &lt;em&gt;(20 points)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you only call out bad behavior when someone is around to see it and provide you with praise for doing so?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you spend more time speaking for an oppressed group than listening to them or promoting their words?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you frequently speak/write/present about the oppressed group without first suggesting that a program/publication/event/etc. speak to members of that group instead? &lt;em&gt;(10 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you take credit for the work of members of the group you are allied with? &lt;em&gt;(10 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt; Without also giving them credit? &lt;em&gt;(100 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt; While claiming they did not do the work? &lt;em&gt;(1000 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you do things that actively harm members of the group you are allied with? &lt;em&gt;(100 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt; Intentionally? &lt;em&gt;(1000 points per incident)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="scoring"&gt;Scoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The higher your score, the less frequently you act as a good ally. Higher scores indicate you are probably
not an ally at all. Below are some arbitrary scoring breakdowns I came up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0-1:&lt;/strong&gt; Either you&amp;rsquo;re an amazingly awesome ally or you lied on the quiz. The latter seems more likely &amp;ndash; shame on you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2-10:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re doing a pretty good job, but remember that being an ally is an &lt;a href="http://www.shakesville.com/2013/04/on-fixed-state-ally-model-vs-process.html"&gt;ongoing process&lt;/a&gt;, so you should continue to work hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11-24:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re making some mistakes and have room for improvement, but you are making good progress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;25-49:&lt;/strong&gt; You make a lot of mistakes, but might still act as an ally at times. You have a lot of room to improve. You should spend more time &lt;a href="/blog/2013/11/02/101-off-limits/"&gt;educating yourself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;50-99:&lt;/strong&gt; You are rarely or never an ally, but might be able to start developing your skills if you&amp;rsquo;re willing to work hard. You need to spend a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of time on &lt;a href="/blog/2013/11/02/101-off-limits/"&gt;educating yourself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;100+:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re not ready to be an ally. Stop claiming you are. &lt;a href="/blog/2013/11/02/101-off-limits/"&gt;Go educate yourself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1000+:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re not even close to being an ally. In fact, you&amp;rsquo;re probably actively harming members of the group you&amp;rsquo;re supposedly allied with. STOP IT. Work on improving asap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5000+:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re not an ally. You&amp;rsquo;re a shitty human being. What the fuck is wrong with you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Blast from the Past: Interviewing Women Candidates</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2014/01/30/blast-from-the-past-interviewing-women-candidates/"/>
    <id>/blog/2014/01/30/blast-from-the-past-interviewing-women-candidates/</id>
    <published>2014-01-31T02:20:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-31T02:20:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Pagano</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, a coworker who understands my enjoyment at rage humor brought me a special present from the past &amp;ndash; a pamphlet titled &amp;ldquo;Interviewing Women Candidates&amp;rdquo; created by the U.S. Civil Service Commission in 1974.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is equal parts hilarious and horrifying how much of this still seems necessary and relevant 40 years later. I&amp;rsquo;m tempted to create a slightly modernized version and start handing copies out at tech events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="pamphlet_page1.png"&gt;&lt;img src="pamphlet_page1.png" alt="pamphlet page 1" width="23%"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="pamphlet_page2.png"&gt;&lt;img src="pamphlet_page2.png" alt="pamphlet page 2" width="23%"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="pamphlet_page3.png"&gt;&lt;img src="pamphlet_page3.png" alt="pamphlet page 3" width="23%"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="pamphlet_page4.png"&gt;&lt;img src="pamphlet_page4.png" alt="pamphlet page 4" width="23%"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to know, sometimes, how to act with someone of another race, another generation, the other sex. What may have been the norm yesterday isn&amp;rsquo;t accepted today and may not be tolerated tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviewing women as candidates or potential applicants is one situation for which the norms are changing. Here are some rules to go by. They are not intended to establish that any specific behavior is legal or illegal, contrary to Federal regulations or not. The perspective is one of the common sense, common courtesy and a professional approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a supervisor filling a vacant position, or as a representative of your agency interviewing potential applicants, you want to do the right thing, to make a favorable impression for your organization and to avoid embarrassment for yourself and the people you interview. This is an attempt to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the right words. Try to remember that the women in your office are not &amp;ldquo;girls&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;gals.&amp;rdquo; And the woman you&amp;rsquo;re interviewing isn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;sweetie&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;honey&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;dear&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; even if you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; a good ol&amp;#39; boy, even if you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; call men you&amp;rsquo;ve never met before things like &amp;ldquo;pal&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;chum.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we please stop arguing about &lt;a href="http://www.lilliechilen.com/woman/"&gt;calling women girls&lt;/a&gt; now that you realize how long this has been considered inappropriate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t inquire into certain areas that are none of our business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Her marital status (or nonmarital arrangements) or plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What her husband does, how he feels about her working, traveling, or anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether she has any children (or plans to) and how many, what ages or sex they are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arrangements for the care of her children.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Her views on birth control, abortion, women&amp;rsquo;s lib.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t bring up your prejudices. You&amp;rsquo;re entitled to them, of course, but you aren&amp;rsquo;t entitled to do anything about them on company time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women shouldn&amp;rsquo;t travel alone, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t travel with men, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t stay overnight in another city.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women aren&amp;rsquo;t aggressive enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are too emotional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They never stick with a job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They won&amp;rsquo;t accept travel assignments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That women want to work only until marriage, or that they all want to marry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That women are absent from work more than men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That they use more sick leave than men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women don&amp;rsquo;t want responsibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can&amp;rsquo;t supervise men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can&amp;rsquo;t supervise women.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aren&amp;rsquo;t interested in certain fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aren&amp;rsquo;t mobile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s ridiculous how many of these prejudices (and that is exactly what they are) still exist today. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a number of these in person and probably seen all of them on Hacker News. I would be thrilled if I never again have someone tell me that women aren&amp;rsquo;t interested in programming because biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t flirt, don&amp;rsquo;t be patronizing (&amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;ll find lots of boyfriends&amp;rdquo;). Don&amp;rsquo;t presume: Interviewers sometimes take advantage of an interviewee&amp;rsquo;s friendliness to act as if there is a degree of friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve heard stories from several friends who had this happen in job interviews within the last year or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t joke. Some men find it embarrassing to behave toward women in a completely businesslike way. It can bring on the same kind of feelings you had as a child when you were trying to lie and thought the smirk you were suppressing must be obvious to everyone. The fact is that when women are treated as adult human beings, they don&amp;rsquo;t notice anything strange about it &amp;ndash; or you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. Let me repeat that. &lt;strong&gt;When women are treated as adult human beings, they don&amp;rsquo;t notice anything strange about it.&lt;/strong&gt; How ridiculous is it that people have to be told that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, in making a selection or recommendation, it is improper to give consideration to such factors as the following:
- That supervisors or managers might prefer men.
- Customers/clients wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want to deal with women.
- Coworkers might object.
- Women&amp;rsquo;s work lacks credibility.
- The job involves travel, or travel with the opposite sex.
- It involves unusual working conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interviewing &amp;ndash; say, on campus &amp;ndash; it is your responsibility as a Federal representative to assure that candidates are scheduled impartially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is improper to place undue emphasis on conditions of employment in the hope of discouraging the candidate, i.e., to solicit a declination. It is for the applicant, not the employer, to decide whether or not she wants the job &amp;ndash; based, of course, on a clear explanation of what the conditions are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, don&amp;rsquo;t indicate your interest in a woman candidate as one whose selection would help improve your EEO picture (it&amp;rsquo;s an insulting suggestion that you&amp;rsquo;d apply different standards).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of men telling women they were hired as tokens. This still happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general rule is that one should treat women applicants and men applicants in the same way. But it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make it right if you also go through the motions of asking men, say, about their prospects for parenthood: The point is that in most cases men have no reason to suppose that an improper significance would be attached to the answer, whereas women do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discriminatory behavior is as improper when it is not intended as when it is, and the appearance can be as important as the reality. That you ask certain questions not related to the job wouldn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily show that you mean to discriminate, but such questions can be used and have been used in a discriminatory way, and women are increasingly aware of and resentful of this. The fact that certain questions are not relevant to consideration for employment is why they are improper when introduced into an employment interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hey, even in 1974, they knew that intent wasn&amp;rsquo;t as important as outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of &lt;em&gt;don&amp;#39;ts&lt;/em&gt;. Where, you may ask, are the &lt;em&gt;do&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt;? What &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; you talk about? Simple: There&amp;rsquo;s the job, its duties and responsibilities. The organization, its missions, programs and achievements. Career possibilities and opportunities for growth, development, advancement. Where the job is located, travel, mobility, equipment and facilities available (especially important with scientists). The individual&amp;rsquo;s qualifications: abilities, experience, education, interests. The wonder is that one can cover all the ground that needs to be covered, let alone have any time left for irrelevancies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh hey, there&amp;rsquo;s so many useful and interesting things to talk to ladies about. Why are you being an asshole again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last rule, though. Don&amp;rsquo;t go the other way: Don&amp;rsquo;t take pains to point out how fair-minded you and your organization are (it will sound phony anyway) or give an instant replay of every female success story. And don&amp;rsquo;t make a big deal about being mature: If you&amp;rsquo;ve decided to go along with &amp;ldquo;Ms.&amp;rdquo; and avoid masculine pronouns when you mean man or woman, that&amp;rsquo;s fine but at least don&amp;rsquo;t put it in italics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this come up a lot from people and organizations who are responsible for poor behavior. Instead of owning it and apologizing, they focus on all the other things they did that supposedly make up for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This guide was written with an awareness that many supervisors and agency representatives are men. While some of the points here obviously apply only to them, most would be applicable regardless of the interviewer&amp;rsquo;s sex.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="pamphlet_page1.png" alt="pamphlet page 1"&gt;
&lt;img src="pamphlet_page2.png" alt="pamphlet page 2"&gt;
&lt;img src="pamphlet_page3.png" alt="pamphlet page 3"&gt;
&lt;img src="pamphlet_page4.png" alt="pamphlet page 4"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Making Mistakes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2014/01/06/on-making-mistakes/"/>
    <id>/blog/2014/01/06/on-making-mistakes/</id>
    <published>2014-01-07T03:46:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-07T03:46:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Pagano</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The topic of making mistakes and apologizing is pretty well tread ground, but I wanted to collect my own thoughts on the matter and figured it couldn&amp;rsquo;t hurt to share. The usual disclaimers about this being my opinion and your mileage may vary apply. Also I say &lt;em&gt;fuck&lt;/em&gt; quite a bit. So, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about making mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistakes are complicated and have many variables. I can&amp;rsquo;t tell you how to handle every specific situation. However, I&amp;rsquo;ve found the following rough steps to be a very useful outline in navigating my own missteps. I recommend considering them and giving them a try. Making mistakes well is an important skill, and you should work on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="expectations"&gt;Expectations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step one&lt;/strong&gt; of making mistakes is realizing that you&amp;rsquo;re going to make them&amp;hellip;a lot. We all fuck up. Every last one of us. You fuck up. I fuck up. Everyone fucks up. Nobody is immune from making mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="you-fucked-up"&gt;You fucked up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step two&lt;/strong&gt; is actually making a mistake. Nobody really &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt; help with this part. We manage to do a pretty good job of it all on our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step three&lt;/strong&gt; is finding out you made a mistake. Maybe you realize the mistake yourself. Maybe a friend points it out kindly. Maybe someone you hurt tells you that you royally fucked up. Maybe someone who is frustrated yells at you and is nasty about it. Or one of a hundred other flavors of learning you have done something wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="processing"&gt;Processing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step four&lt;/strong&gt; is coming to terms with making a mistake. This part can be hard and painful and nasty. I recommend handling this step as privately as possible to avoid putting the nasty parts on display, which often leads to even more mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very common initial reaction is to be defensive. You probably didn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt; to make a mistake or cause harm. Unfortunately, you did whether you meant to or not. It&amp;rsquo;s ok to feel defensive &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s an incredibly human response. However, it&amp;rsquo;s usually one you want to keep to yourself (and maybe a few close friends). Responding defensively is an intentional act that defends your mistake instead of admitting fault. It can do additional harm and is unlikely to improve the situation. Take a little time to sit with any feelings of defensiveness. They will likely pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the mistake was pointed out by someone else, a common reaction is to be frustrated or angry with them. The previous advice about defensiveness stands. I recommend looking at what they did as an act of kindness, even if presented in a hostile way. Mistakes can make you look bad and follow you for a long time when not resolved. Thanks to that person, you know what you did wrong and have a chance to make amends. The person who pointed it out isn&amp;rsquo;t the problem &amp;ndash; your mistake is. It can be difficult to deal with anger, frustration, or hostility, but mistakes have consequences, and they&amp;rsquo;re not always easy. People who have been hurt aren&amp;rsquo;t always nice, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the fact that you made a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another common feeling is remorse. To feel shame or disappointment in yourself. This is understandable, especially if your mistake caused harm. You may be sad, but remember that your sadness isn&amp;rsquo;t as immediately important as fixing the mistake nor is it a replacement for making amends. Once you&amp;rsquo;re done, you can take as much time as you feel appropriate to beat yourself up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Handle a mistake well, and you can actually come out with more respect than when you started. On the flip side, responding poorly makes you look even worse than the initial mistake. Choose wisely. There are no do-overs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="atonement"&gt;Atonement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step five&lt;/strong&gt; is taking steps to make amends for your mistake. This will vary a lot depending on what you did and who you harmed. I can&amp;rsquo;t give you an exact script, but I find the following steps to be pretty useful and effective in a lot of situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clearly identify and articulate what you did wrong and any harm that it caused. Avoid (or if you feel compelled to bring it up, dramatically minimize) discussion of what you intended. Good intent is certainly better than bad, but your good intentions don&amp;rsquo;t make up for a harmful outcome. Mentioning your intent often is seen as making excuses, detracts from the quality of an apology, and makes you seem less sincere.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apologize for the harm you caused. &lt;strong&gt;DO NOT&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;apologize&amp;rdquo; for someone else being offended, include caveats, or use any wording that puts the fault on anyone besides yourself. &lt;em&gt;Your&lt;/em&gt; actions caused the harm. Own that if you&amp;rsquo;re going to apologize. A &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-apology_apology"&gt;faux apology&lt;/a&gt; is often worse than no apology at all. Keep it simple. Something like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m sorry I did X&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I apologize for hurting Y&amp;rdquo; often works.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ask if there is anything you can do to make amends for the harm caused. Listen carefully. If possible, do what is asked of you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id="progress"&gt;Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step six&lt;/strong&gt; is making progress. Unless you&amp;rsquo;ve done something exceptionally horrible, you get to move on from mistakes. However, moving on should not mean forgetting and thus dooming yourself to repeat your mistakes. Analyze what you did wrong and try your best to avoid a repeat. This may include additional self-education or work on your part. It&amp;rsquo;s totally worth it to not hurt someone and go through all this again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Going Veg*n...Again</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2014/01/01/going-veg-n-again/"/>
    <id>/blog/2014/01/01/going-veg-n-again/</id>
    <published>2014-01-02T02:03:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-01-02T02:03:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Julie Pagano</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying to go mostly vegetarian again. &amp;ldquo;Mostly&amp;rdquo; meaning that I&amp;rsquo;ll occasionally allow myself to have seafood (mmmm, sushi). I&amp;rsquo;m not doing this as a silly new year&amp;rsquo;s resolution &amp;ndash; I just waited until after the holidays to make holiday cooking easier on my parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve tried some flavor of veg*n a few times in the past. I&amp;rsquo;d love some support and accountability from my friends to try to help it stick this time, so please feel free to share tips (&lt;a href="https://github.com/juliepagano/juliepagano.com/issues/35"&gt;add info on github&lt;/a&gt; or tweet at me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to keep track of the info people share with me and share it with others, so I&amp;rsquo;ll collect it here. These are mostly recommendations from others, so I can&amp;rsquo;t personally vouch for them. I&amp;rsquo;ll add notes as I try things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cookbooks"&gt;Cookbooks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/Jvjqce"&gt;How to Cook Everything Vegetarian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1hhaBkK"&gt;Isa Does It&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/Jvf2da"&gt;La Dolce Vegan!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1erlMlT"&gt;Rebar: Modern Food Cookbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1cn1DOc"&gt;Veg: River Cottage Everyday&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1hhayFw"&gt;Vegan Brunch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1gozRlY"&gt;Veganomicon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1cmZ5zo"&gt;Vegetarian Cooking for Everyone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="recipe-sites"&gt;Recipe sites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://thelazyveggie.tumblr.com/"&gt;The Lazy Veggie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://newlyveg.com/"&gt;NewlyVeg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://plantbasedonabudget.com/"&gt;Plant Based on a Budget&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://plantpoweredkitchen.com/"&gt;Plant Powered Kitchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.theppk.com/"&gt;Post Punk Kitchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://thugkitchen.com/"&gt;Thug Kitchen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://vegandad.blogspot.com/"&gt;VeganDad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://vegweb.com/"&gt;VegWeb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="products"&gt;Products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daiya (vegan cheese)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earth Balance (vegan butter alternative)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.uptonsnaturals.com/"&gt;Upton&amp;rsquo;s Naturals Seitan&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;I tried the Italian flavor, and I think it cured me of missing italian sausage&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="miscellaneous-vegetarian-notes"&gt;Miscellaneous vegetarian notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="stuff-that&amp;#39;s-not-vegetarian-(but-might-not-be-obvious)"&gt;Stuff that&amp;rsquo;s not vegetarian (but might not be obvious)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jello, marshmallows, and other stuff with &lt;strong&gt;gelatin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parmesan cheese and other cheeses that use &lt;strong&gt;rennet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some baked good mixes (check for &lt;strong&gt;lard&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some beer and wine (often not labeled one way or the other)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="miscellaneous-vegan-notes"&gt;Miscellaneous vegan notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earth Balance is recommended as a butter replacement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daiya is recommended as a cheese replacement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="local-options-in-pittsburgh"&gt;Local options in Pittsburgh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="lists"&gt;Lists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.happycow.net/north_america/usa/pennsylvania/pittsburgh/"&gt;Happy Cow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.urbanspoon.com/f/23/2253/Pittsburgh/Vegetarian-Restaurants"&gt;UrbanSpoon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://veganpittsburgh.org/"&gt;Vegan Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.yelp.com/search?find_desc=Vegan+Restaurants&amp;amp;amp;find_loc=Pittsburgh%2C+PA"&gt;Yelp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="restaurants-i-frequent"&gt;Restaurants I frequent&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.aladdinseatery.com/"&gt;Aladdin&amp;rsquo;s Eatery&lt;/a&gt; - Squirrel Hill - Mediterranean - &lt;em&gt;cheap and yummy Mediterranean with lots of vegetarian and some vegan options&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://bangkokbalconypgh.com/"&gt;Bangkok Balcony&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.silkelephant.net/"&gt;Silk Elephant&lt;/a&gt; - Squirrel Hill - Thai - &lt;em&gt;These restaurants have very similar menus, both of which include awesome tofu dishes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.doublewidegrill.com/"&gt;Double Wide Grill&lt;/a&gt; - South Side - American - &lt;em&gt;Really delicious seitan wings and the veggie burger is pretty good.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.madmex.com/"&gt;Mad Mex&lt;/a&gt; - Shadyside (and other locations) - Mexican/American &lt;em&gt;American-style Mexican food with some decent vegetarian options. I&amp;rsquo;m especially fond of the tofu tacos.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.otbbicyclecafe.com/"&gt;Over the Bar Bicycle Cafe&lt;/a&gt; - South Side - American - &lt;em&gt;yummy salads and sandwiches in a cute biker friendly bar with fun bike decor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ramenbarpittsburgh.com/"&gt;Ramen Bar&lt;/a&gt; - Squirrel Hill - Ramen - &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m fond of the vegetarian ramen with a shoyou base and extra garlic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="groceries"&gt;Groceries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;East End Food Co-op - &lt;em&gt;a lot of the same stuff as Whole Foods, but locally owned&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giant Eagle Market District (some regular Giant Eagles have veg stuff, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty hit or miss)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trader Joes - &lt;em&gt;affordable, but pretty hit or miss with what they&amp;rsquo;ll have&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whole Foods - &lt;em&gt;expensive, but lots of options&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
