<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2013-11-02T22:07:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>101 off limits</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/11/02/101-off-limits/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/11/02/101-off-limits/</id>
    <published>2013-11-02T22:07:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-11-02T22:07:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I keep saying that impromptu, unwanted feminism 101 discussions are exhausting and not a good use of my resources. Then people ask what I mean by 101, so I&amp;#8217;m starting to make a list. This list will change over time - I recommend checking back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend checking this list before engaging with me about feminism if you&amp;#8217;re new to it. It&amp;#8217;ll save both of us a lot of time and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='diversity_in_tech'&gt;Diversity in tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='women_arent_equally_represented_in_tech_because_biology'&gt;Women aren&amp;#8217;t equally represented in tech because biology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope. This argument is bad and the science does not support it. Unfortunately, every time you say this out loud, you are contributing to cultural problems that do decrease the number of women in tech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also see, &lt;a href='http://www.slideshare.net/terriko/how-does-biology-explain-the-low-numbers-of-women-in-cs-hint-it-doesnt'&gt;How Does Biology Explain the Low Numbers of Women in CS? Hint: it doesn&amp;#8217;t&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='minorityonly_spaces_are_ist'&gt;Minority-only spaces are &lt;em&gt;ist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope. You keep using that word, I don&amp;#8217;t think it means what you think it means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='youre_giving_minority_an_unfair_advantage_by_helping_them'&gt;You&amp;#8217;re giving &amp;#60;minority&amp;gt; an unfair advantage by helping them&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope. The post &lt;a href='https://medium.com/thoughts-on-society/a1345b36b91b'&gt;Why do women try to get ahead by pulling men down?&lt;/a&gt; uses some good metaphors that might help you understand why this is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='minority_demographic_is_underrepresented_in_tech_because_they_dont_try_hard_enough'&gt;&amp;#60;minority demographic&amp;gt; is underrepresented in tech because they don&amp;#8217;t try hard enough&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope. It sure sounds like you&amp;#8217;re saying an entire demographic is lazy. Not cool and not true. Try evaluating what sort of cultural issues discourage that demographic and what privileges make tech more accessible for the highly representated demographics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='diversity_at_conferences'&gt;Diversity at Conferences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read Ashe&amp;#8217;s awesome posts &lt;a href='http://ashedryden.com/blog/so-you-want-to-put-on-a-diverse-inclusive-conference'&gt;So you want to put on a diverse, inclusive conference&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://ashedryden.com/blog/increasing-diversity-at-your-conference'&gt;Increasing diversity at your conference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='rape_culture'&gt;Rape Culture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='explain_rape_culture_to_me'&gt;Explain rape culture to me.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Go read &lt;a href='http://www.shakesville.com/2009/10/rape-culture-101.html'&gt;rape culture 101&lt;/a&gt;. Then read it again. And again. And again. Pretty much read that on the daily until it&amp;#8217;s seeped in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent an evening explaining this on twitter and sharing resources. Check out the &lt;a href='http://storify.com/juliepagano/sexual-assault-educational-resources'&gt;storify&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='i_dont_think_rape_culture_exists'&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think rape culture exists.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href='#explain_rape_culture_to_me'&gt;Explain rape culture to me&lt;/a&gt;. If you still think it&amp;#8217;s not a thing, please don&amp;#8217;t ever speak to me about this. Honestly, I&amp;#8217;m not really interested in engaging with people who are aware of what rape culture is and deny its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='rape_jokes_are_funny'&gt;Rape jokes are funny&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nope. They&amp;#8217;re really not. Additionally, they contribute to rape culture. When you tell them, you are also contributing to rape culture. You probably didn&amp;#8217;t know that before. It&amp;#8217;s ok. Now you know. Make a change for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://tacoboutthatbutt.tumblr.com/post/49458621565/to-all-those-who-dont-think-the-rape-joke-was-a'&gt;This comment about rape jokes&lt;/a&gt; may also help you understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='women_need_to_stop_being_so_paranoid_all_the_time'&gt;Women need to stop being so paranoid all the time.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go read &lt;a href='http://kateharding.net/2009/10/08/guest-blogger-starling-schrodinger%E2%80%99s-rapist-or-a-guy%E2%80%99s-guide-to-approaching-strange-women-without-being-maced/'&gt;Schroedinger&amp;#8217;s Rapist&lt;/a&gt;. This may help you understand. Alternatively, you may have read this already and that&amp;#8217;s why you&amp;#8217;re saying this to me. It&amp;#8217;s not paranoia when the rape and violence statistics are what they are. Please don&amp;#8217;t tell us how to react to our own lived experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='how_should_a_community_handle_sexual_assault'&gt;How should a community handle sexual assault?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend reviewing my other resources in this section and then moving forward with an accountability process. Below are some good resources about accountability processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.creative-interventions.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/4.F.CI-Toolkit-Tools-Taking-Accountability-Pre-Release-Version-06.2012.pdf'&gt;from Creative Interventions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.transformativejustice.eu/wp-content/uploads/2010/11/Taking-Risks.-CARA.pdf'&gt;from Transformative Justice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='allies'&gt;Allies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='your_behavior_is_pushing_away_allies'&gt;Your behavior is pushing away allies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;re not being a good ally when you&amp;#8217;re telling members of the oppressed group you&amp;#8217;re supposedly allied with how to behave. You and I may just have different definitions of what being an ally means. I highly recommend reading about &lt;a href='http://www.shakesville.com/2013/04/on-fixed-state-ally-model-vs-process.html'&gt;the fixed state ally model versus the process ally model&lt;/a&gt;. I subscribe to the latter, and it sounds like you subscribe to the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='but_im_an_ally_why_are_you_attacking_me_generally_in_response_to_disagreement'&gt;But I&amp;#8217;m an ally! Why are you attacking me? (generally in response to disagreement)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disagreement is not attacking. Being an ally does not shield you from criticism when you make mistakes. Being an ally does not make you an expert on the lived experiences of the people who are claiming to be an ally to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also &lt;a href='#your_behavior_is_pushing_away_allies'&gt;Your behavior is pushing away allies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='miscellaneous'&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id='im_not_ist_but'&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not &lt;em&gt;ist but&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me stop you right there. Sentences that start this way very rarely end well. Just don&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='why_do_you_hate_men'&gt;Why do you hate men?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t. I like lots of men just fine. In fact, I even love some of them. Sure, I have contempt for some men, but it&amp;#8217;s because of their individual bad behavior, not because of their gender. That being said, I am pretty sick of &lt;a href='http://www.shakesville.com/2012/03/terrible-bargain-we-have-regretfully.html'&gt;the terrible bargain we&amp;#8217;ve regretfully struck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='if_you_wont_teach_me_how_will_i_learn'&gt;If you won&amp;#8217;t teach me, how will I learn?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are not entitled to my (or anyone else&amp;#8217;s) attention or efforts, especially on demand. There are tons of writings (books, blog posts, journal articles, etc.) on all of these topics. I&amp;#8217;m pretty sure you&amp;#8217;re capable of finding some of them if you try even a little bit. I have limited time, and I would much rather spend it on other things that make me happy and help others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be a lot more likely to give you my time if you schedule it with me and do the bare minimum of research first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='i_dont_like_your_tone_youd_catch_more_flies_with_honey_etc_etc'&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t like your tone. You&amp;#8217;d catch more flies with honey. etc. etc.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called a &lt;a href='http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Tone_argument'&gt;tone argument&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s a well-known derailing technique that is patronizing and dismissive. Some of the things feminism has to say are hard - there&amp;#8217;s no nice way to say them. It&amp;#8217;s also not my job to act pleasing and friendly on all occasions. If you regularly find my tone to not match your interests, feel free to find another source - I won&amp;#8217;t be mad. I will be frustrated and contemptuous if you use a tone argument on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='youre_being_too_angry'&gt;You&amp;#8217;re being too angry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href='http://www.shakesville.com/2008/05/feminism-101-on-anger.html'&gt;Feminism 101: On Anger&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, groups of marginalized people are often accused of being angry when what they are is frustrated. &lt;a href='http://www.shakesville.com/2013/03/an-observation_28.html'&gt;Sometimes, we&amp;#8217;re not angry, we&amp;#8217;re dissatisfied.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='why_the_hell_do_you_keep_talking_about_spoons'&gt;Why the hell do you keep talking about spoons?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go read about &lt;a href='http://www.butyoudontlooksick.com/wpress/articles/written-by-christine/the-spoon-theory/'&gt;the spoon theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='thats_reverseism'&gt;That&amp;#8217;s reverse-&lt;em&gt;ism!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reverse-sexism/racism/*ism isn&amp;#8217;t a thing. There&amp;#8217;s just sexism/racism/*ism, and there&amp;#8217;s a reasonable likelihood that you don&amp;#8217;t know how they work. oppression = prejudice + power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='im_just_playing_devils_advocate'&gt;I&amp;#8217;m just playing devil&amp;#8217;s advocate.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be honest, it feels like you&amp;#8217;re saying terrible things and trying to shield yourself from criticism by yelling &amp;#8220;devil&amp;#8217;s advocate&amp;#8221; while doing so. Maybe that&amp;#8217;s not what you&amp;#8217;re doing. It doesn&amp;#8217;t matter a whole lot because either way I don&amp;#8217;t want to have a conversation with someone pretending to take the side of some hyperbolic other. Please don&amp;#8217;t initiate these conversations with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='not_all_guys_are_like_that'&gt;Not all guys are like that!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://nudityandnerdery.tumblr.com/post/63995327460/see-what-you-need-to-understand-is-that-not-all'&gt;Read this post.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='why_are_you_so_easily_offended'&gt;Why are you so easily offended?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://hoydenabouttown.com/20110403.9735/dont-mistake-expressing-contempt-for-taking-offense/'&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not offended, I&amp;#8217;m contemptuous.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id='what_are_some_other_good_resources'&gt;What are some other good resources?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.shakesville.com/2010/01/feminism-101.html'&gt;Feminism 101 posts from Shakesville&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I think I’m in an emotionally abusive relationship…with the tech community</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/09/23/i-think-i-m-in-an-emotionally-abusive-relationship-with-the-tech-community/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/09/23/i-think-i-m-in-an-emotionally-abusive-relationship-with-the-tech-community/</id>
    <published>2013-09-24T00:35:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-24T00:35:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been feeling some burnout this year as a programmer. It’s not coming from my job, which I enjoy and is a great balance of challenging and supportive. No, it’s the rest of it. The community. The part that in theory is optional, but in reality helps build the relationships and knowledge that can be critical to one’s development and career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just me. I see this in other programmers, both in person and online. There’s a whole group of us just barely making it. Regularly running on fumes, refueling just enough to stave off the burnout for another week. Every now and again, I see one leave the community (and sometimes programming altogether) because they ran out of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, I think I finally figured out what it is. I noticed the symptoms - what some might refer to as “red flags.” I think we’re in an emotionally abusive relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did we get here? Why is it this bad? Why are we staying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s always been the &lt;a href='http://juliepagano.com/blog/2013/03/24/my-experiences-in-tech-death-by-1000-paper-cuts/'&gt;microaggressions&lt;/a&gt;. I didn’t always notice them, but eventually they accumulated enough that I was buried. I couldn’t ignore them any more. Recently, a new symptom finally hit the point where I couldn’t pretend it isn’t there. &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaslighting'&gt;Gaslighting&lt;/a&gt; (or at least something very akin to it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaslighting is a symptom of emotional abuse, so it was a disturbing discovery. Out of curiosity, I looked up other symptoms of emotional abuse. An upsettingly long list of them were all too easy to identify with. Fuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Am I imagining things? Am I being hyperbolic? Have I finally lost it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming yourself and thinking you’re crazy is one of the symptoms of emotional abuse. The whole point of gaslighting is to convince the victim and those around them that the victim is irrational and making things up. Scary part is that it makes it hard to speak out and tell others what’s going on. You probably won’t believe me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do they belittle your accomplishments, your aspirations, your plans or even who you are? Do they have unrealistic expectations?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re often accused of whining on the internet, of not doing enough. How dare we ask for diversity unless we’re willing to fix it? Our attemps to do so are never enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many work for free trying to help, missing out on the income they so desperately need to live and thrive, but it’s not enough. Many try to help with the pipeline problem by teaching, but it’s not enough. Others provide support and mentorship, but it’s not enough. Others help with outreach, but it’s not enough. We speak at conferences, but not enough of them, even though the travel and expenses can be quite costly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, we have to be great programmers - average just won’t do. We’re expected to do ALL THE THINGS, but even when we try, we are belittled. We can seemingly never do enough to get an equal seat at the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guy suggests doing something many have been doing for years and receives support and accolates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do they constantly correct or chastise you because your behavior is “inappropriate?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we had a dollar for every time someone told us our behavior was inappropriate, we wouldn’t have to worry about all this. We’d be so rich we’d never have to work again. We could buy our own private island and sail away. Sadly, nobody pays us for this. They just ignore our comments and chastise us for saying things in a way that many others get away with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;If only you were nicer.&amp;#8221; &amp;#8220;This isn’t how you talk to your ‘allies’.&amp;#8221; &amp;#8220;Stop being a bitch.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do they continually have “boundary violations” and disrespect your valid requests? Do they try to turn everyone against you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just recently, friends and I had someone in a position of power ignore our boundaries. Despite requests to the contrary, this person insisted on attempting to talk about something I had explicitly made off limits. Going so far as telling mutual acquaintances about the situation in an attempt to get their assistance in forcing the discussion. Going so far as telling others the story in an attempt to paint us in a negative light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t stop when we asked for it to. My understanding is it only eventually stopped because a male friend asked. Our boundaries don’t count until someone else asserts them for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you feel helpless, like you’re trapped in the relationship? Do they limit your access to work, money or material resources?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said before, the community is theoretically optional. However, the reality is that it can be critical for networking, learning, finding resources, and attaining jobs. Many feel obligated to stay for our careers - terrified of speaking up for fear of retribution. Most feel they don’t have the skills to leave and find a job in a different field. They’re trapped in this emotionally abusive relationship. Leaving would mean giving up their livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do they have trouble apologizing? When you complain do they say that “it was just a joke” and that you are too sensitive? Do they treat you so badly that you’re embarrassed for your friends or family to see? Do you feel emotionally numb or helpless?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. I’m not going to elaborate on all these for the sake of brevity and my tired brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are they physically abusive?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, yes. The community often protects physical abusers and sexual assaulters in our communities. The information is often hard to find because part of the emotional abuse is feeling unsafe discussing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why am I so tired all the time? How much longer can I do this? What’s the price I’ll have to pay?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am making the hard decision to remove myself from as much of the situation as I can. I plan to focus my time and efforts largely on my awesome job and my work on Girl Develop It. I’d love to speak a few times next year, but I will be limiting myself to conferences that are committed to encouraging diversity and include policies that create a safe space. I’ll be avoiding ones that continually include toxic people and behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not advocating this as the right decision for everyone in this situation. It’s just what I feel is needed right now for me. My only recommendations are to find the support you need and make sure to prioritize self care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sad I have to pull back, to do less, but my health and sanity is more important than networking and my cred with the community. This is the price, and it is too high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comments are closed on this post. If this angers you, you’re part of the problem. If you’re sad about what you read and have the energy, please try to shape the community into a space that looks different. It doesn’t have to be this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: As I’ve indicated on twitter, this is not a criticism of the conference I was at this weekend - the timing is unfortunate. The organizers hosted a lovely conference, and I was honored to speak at it. They did an awesome job at having a great diverse lineup (my fave is still the 11 year old young woman who loves ruby and dancing) and a code of conduct.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Julie's Lean In Livetweets</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/04/03/julie-s-lean-in-livetweets/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/04/03/julie-s-lean-in-livetweets/</id>
    <published>2013-04-04T02:07:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-04-04T02:07:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://storify.com/juliepagano/julie-s-lean-in-livetweets'&gt;Julie&amp;#8217;s Lean In Livetweets&lt;/a&gt; If you missed the live part of my Lean In livetweeting, you can check out most of it over at Storify.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In case you didn’t know, my technology will be intersectional or it will be BULLSHIT</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/03/25/in-case-you-didn-t-know-my-technology-will-be-intersectional-or-it-will-be-bullshit/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/03/25/in-case-you-didn-t-know-my-technology-will-be-intersectional-or-it-will-be-bullshit/</id>
    <published>2013-03-26T02:04:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-26T02:04:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I mentioned this on twitter late last night and again today, but I want to repeat it here for those who missed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the message you took from my posts is that we should treat women special, please understand that you got it wrong. We should be making everyone feel welcome in tech. The experiences I described are just my personal examples of areas where we may be falling short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiences I described are largely about being a woman in the tech industry because I am a woman - that’s my lived experience. I cannot speak directly to the experiences of people who are black or transgender or disabled or hispanic or gay or any other number of underrepresented groups that have it just as hard, if not dramatically harder, than people like me. It’s not right for me to try to appropriate their experiences, but many of them are dying from 1000 paper cuts too. They have their own stories to tell, and you should listen to them too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not ok with a movement that pushes forward to claim a place for women in tech while leaving other people behind. That’s just moving the goal post, and it’s not sufficient. This isn’t about building a better position for myself (and others like me), it’s about pushing for a better community for everyone. Anything short of that feels like selfish bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received a lot of kind words in response to my posts, and I appreciated every one of them. You are good people, and you clearly care. Please share your own stories - I will support you in doing so. I want to hear a multitude of voices, and I don’t want them all to sound like mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome you to join me in screaming the only catchphrase that I can seem to muster these days. MY TECHNOLOGY WILL BE INTERSECTIONAL OR IT WILL BE BULLSHIT!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My experiences in tech: Death by 1000 paper cuts</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/03/24/my-experiences-in-tech-death-by-1000-paper-cuts/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/03/24/my-experiences-in-tech-death-by-1000-paper-cuts/</id>
    <published>2013-03-24T19:08:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-24T19:08:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href='http://juliepagano.com/blog/2013/03/23/my-experiences-in-tech-once-upon-an-internship/' title='My experiences in tech: Once upon an internship'&gt;Once Upon an Internship&lt;/a&gt;, I learned early that sometimes being a software engineer means death by 1000 cuts because you don&amp;#8217;t have the power to make it stop. Even the tiniest little things add up to something big - sometimes it&amp;#8217;s really death by 1000 paper cuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cuts started early. I&amp;#8217;m discouraged and humiliated in math classes throughout my school years to the point where I still get anxious doing math in front of others despite being good at it in private.  A high school teacher tells me that I shouldn&amp;#8217;t go to college for engineering, but instead something nurturing (you know, what women are good for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My college classes have next to no women in them. A professor makes creepy comments about &amp;#8220;geeky girls&amp;#8221; during class. One of my few female classmates tells me she&amp;#8217;s just doing this to prove her father wrong. Classmates don&amp;#8217;t take me seriously until I scream. The first time I learned that you get to be a bitch or you get to be ignored - a choice that would later follow me to the working world. Four years of paper cuts. Four years of pushing myself too hard because I wanted to prove something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly every technical conference I attend has at least one person with a microphone making a comment along the lines of &amp;#8221;my wife/girlfriend doesn&amp;#8217;t understand technology and gives me shit for being interested in it.&amp;#8221; It&amp;#8217;s clearly intended to be a joke that the audience will identify with, and most of them do because theses conferences are largely straight and male. For those of us who aren&amp;#8217;t, it&amp;#8217;s a regular signal that we&amp;#8217;re not considered, that maybe we don&amp;#8217;t belong. The heavy drinking makes some of us feel unsafe. A paper cut for every conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an old job, someone in authority pats me on the head to dismiss an argument I&amp;#8217;m making about something at work. As though I was a child - a thing he&amp;#8217;d be unlikely to do with a male coworker. Same person makes comments when I wear makeup to work - I feel uncomfortable doing so again. I&amp;#8217;m asked to take notes in meetings where I am a technical lead and should be actively participating. Male coworkers make comments about stalking women on facebook and looking at images of booth babes in work meetings (some later apologize). Others say that front-end development isn&amp;#8217;t real software engineering. I suspect I&amp;#8217;m paid less than male colleagues (perhaps paranoia, perhaps real - it&amp;#8217;s a hard thing to verify). Problems are easiest to resolve by finding a new job - this is what I do (thankfully the new job is much better). A thousand paper cuts for the working world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time I try to push to make things better, I am guaranteed a patronizing response from someone. If I had a dollar for every time someone suggested that some demographics just aren&amp;#8217;t biologically predisposed to be good at programming (&lt;a href='http://www.slideshare.net/terriko/how-does-biology-explain-the-low-numbers-of-women-in-cs-hint-it-doesnt'&gt;even though research does not support this argument&lt;/a&gt;), I&amp;#8217;d be rich. On more than one occasion, I&amp;#8217;ve had people try to engage me in arguments about the importance of diversity only to later claim they &amp;#8220;were playing devil&amp;#8217;s advocate&amp;#8221; or doing it &amp;#8220;for the lulz.&amp;#8221; I&amp;#8217;ve had people &lt;a href='http://juliepagano.com/blog/2013/01/13/thoughts-on-a-diversity-discussion/' title='Thoughts on a diversity discussion'&gt;derail diversity discussions&lt;/a&gt; to victim blame and try to speak for the minority that they were not a member of. I&amp;#8217;ve had people claim minority-only safe spaces are sexist. A paper cut for every time I speak up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before someone suggests that these patronizing responses are just jerks on the internet, no, that&amp;#8217;s not the case. I get these responses fairly regularly in person. From people I&amp;#8217;ve worked with. From people who know me. From prominent members of some tech communities. From people who should know better. The cuts are deeper when they&amp;#8217;re real people because you can&amp;#8217;t just turn them off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuts I don&amp;#8217;t feel safe posting here because they&amp;#8217;re too personal or I fear the consequences&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention one of the above, and someone tells me that I&amp;#8217;m just looking for things to get angry about. As though my feelings are not valid. Maybe they don&amp;#8217;t understand that probably wasn&amp;#8217;t the only thing that happened that day or that week or that month or the duration of my career. That I can&amp;#8217;t detach and view these things in isolation. That no matter how tough I get, how thick my skin, the paper cuts still hurt. I&amp;#8217;m not the only one covered in bandaids trying to stanch the bleeding and focus on programming because it&amp;#8217;s a thing that I love. I&amp;#8217;m terrified of the day that it becomes terminal, the day myself or one of my friends becomes another statistic in the book of &amp;#8220;they leave and they don&amp;#8217;t come back.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My experiences in tech: Adventures outside the workplace</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/2013/03/23/my-experiences-in-tech-adventures-outside-the-workplace/"/>
    <id>/blog/2013/03/23/my-experiences-in-tech-adventures-outside-the-workplace/</id>
    <published>2013-03-24T03:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-24T03:30:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the issues I mentioned in my &lt;a href='http://juliepagano.com/blog/2013/03/23/my-experiences-in-tech-once-upon-an-internship/'&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; took place at intern lunches that were optional and off-site at local restaurants. Is professional behavior required at social events between colleagues that don’t take place on company property, time, or expense? I went through my list again and noticed that many of my negative experiences happened in this hazy grey area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who only know me now, you may be surprised to hear that I was once very quiet, reserved, and passive. Early in my career, I was just trying to navigate being in the working world and trying to get along. Sometimes this meant going to the bar after work with coworkers to shoot the shit, complain about work, and just generally socialize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rarely minded when these evenings at the bar included some sexualized comments – I was mostly amused by the limited and heterocentric knowledge of my coworkers. We weren’t at work, and I can enjoy a good general sexual joke that isn’t at anyone’s expense. The problem is that conversations didn’t always stop there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On more than one occasion, talk would veer towards sexualizing female coworkers. It was a comment about how hot one of the new employees was or a joke about looking up the intern’s skirt while she changed lightbulbs (apparently she was asking for it by not wearing pants). Rarely (if ever) were these same coworkers discussed for their merits at their job – in fact sometimes they were discussed negatively in these regards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was assumed this conversation was ok as long as the mentioned parties weren’t there and that nobody in participation minded (again, nobody can hear us). This brings us back to my prior comment about how meek I was then. In these situations, I felt I had a choice: complain and stop getting invited to the bar, or put up with it and get included in social outings with my coworkers. At the time, I chose the latter. I’m still angry with myself about this, but I’m mostly upset that I was put in a position where I had to make a choice like that. These conversations were another reminder that some people in the software industry see women as sex objects first and engineers second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another time, a group of coworkers created an after-work club (basically just a group of people going to the bar) with the sole intention of excluding and mocking another coworker they did not like. The name of their club was a twist on the name of a professional organization for minorities this coworker helped organize and was rightly proud of. This kind of behavior made me feel like I’d been transported back to high school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of us who vocally disagreed with this “club” were argued with for not joining the mob. “But &amp;#60;targeted coworker&amp;gt; is lazy and bad at their job.” “Management won’t fire them.” “Their constant mentions of &amp;#60;minority professional organization&amp;gt; are annoying.” “All the cool kids are doing it.” As if any of these things justify bullying. The lack of reflection from the people doing this, many of which were probably bullied in school themselves, was astounding. The club didn’t last long, but the fact that it existed at all disgusts me to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it fair to police every action coworkers take in this hazy grey area outside of work? We could probably go round and round about that all day. It’s legitimately difficult to figure out where one should draw those lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The part that worries me about the incidents described above is not that someone said or did something distasteful outside of work hours. We all do that. What I’m worried about is that these actions are indicative of motivations that also likely infect the professional world. Coworkers would later become managers of the employees they sexualized at the bar. Is that a problem? The “cool kids” club created a mob mentality. Is it easy to turn that off when the mob is at work?&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
